U all right IC say Lombard is the next
company that we're focusing on uh net
earned premium has risen by 20%
yearonear underwriting losses have
declined combined ratio is looking a
little better let's bring in Gopal
Balachandran chief financial officer of
the company who's with us now to take
some questions Gopal good morning
Prashant this side uh you know so for 20
FI25 gross premium grew 10% net earn
premium grew 17%
uh can
F526 be a better year on both these
fronts and what is the growth that
you're baking in on these two metrices
for the coming year. So good morning
Prashant to you and all to you and to
all of your viewers. Uh so let me just
kind of put this in context. Um I think
when we started FI25 what we had kind of
talked about is uh from an ICO
standpoint we expect to have an
outperformance with respect to topline
growth and that is exactly what we have
been able to end the year with. I think
the industry grew at about 6.2% 2% and
on a gross direct premium basis IC is
Lombard has grown roughly 210 basis
points ahead of the market and pretty
much on expected lines I think even on
the combined ratio front as you rightly
mentioned I think the trajectory is
something that we have been able to see
an improvement getting delivered and
more importantly the return on equity
range that we had been talking about
between the 16 to 18% I think we have
been able to kind of pretty much uh live
up to the expectations uh now to your
point on how do we see things playing
out for FI26 6 I think across different
segments I think the the the road that's
kind of laid down looks very very
promising whether you look at the uh
infrastructure investments that and
logistics uh coming in on the commercial
lines pricing uptick again happening in
that segment health looking quite
promising uh continuing to uh look to
exhibit a double digit growth and even
motor uh I think in terms of how do we
see things playing out in the subsequent
year uh looks promising. So all in all,
I think what we would kind of continue
to pencil in is to outperform the
industry in that range of as we keep
saying between 200 to 200 basis points
in so far as topline is concerned and
obviously a trajectory to see an
improvement in combined
sorry 100 to 200 over industry. That is
correct. U okay
uh on on combined ratio Gopal you
managed to protect the 102.5 level will
it get difficult to improve from here on
and could you specifically give us what
are you looking at for 26 so I think
directionally prashant uh obviously what
we have been able to deliver is a
consistent improvement in combined
yearon year uh that's what we had kind
of spoken about as well and uh even in
fact at the beginning of the year
honestly if you look at in our April 24
earnings call. We did kind of expect the
market to be slightly more semblance in
so far as combined ratios are concerned.
But if you look at the 9-month numbers,
the industry has actually seen an
adverse development in the overall
combined. In fact, it has kind of moved
by about 100 basis points from 112% the
previous year 9 months. So the key thing
to watch out for is how what direction
does the market take and uh in that
context is how we will be kind of
positioning our opportunities. uh but
everything remaining the same definitely
we would want to see an improvement in
the combined going ahead and more
importantly as I said the return on
equity range that we want to continue to
start exhibiting to the stakeholders
will be within that 18 to 20%.
Uh Gopal I just want to focus on the
motor segment a little bit uh because
some of the broker notes this morning
are pointing out how the growth in motor
is maybe you know a little soft compared
to what the expectations would have
been. one obviously is a it's a straight
function of sale of new vehicles and
those numbers have been a little weak
but um also I mean what are your
expectations from that business and are
you expecting uh uh an increase in the
third party motor third party rates
anytime soon? Yes, good morning to you.
I think let me answer the second part
first. uh I think third party is
something where for maybe for a
reasonable number of years uh I think
there has been in that sense not a price
increase that we have seen uh as an
industry I think we have made
representations to the uh regulator who
in consultation with the government kind
of notifies the price change uh thus far
we haven't necessarily heard anything uh
from them so far but obviously as I said
we have made the right representations
and in case if the final notifications
comes through with a price change that's
august very very positive both for the
industry at large and specifically in
the context wise it will be a great
great positive but but your first point
in terms of how we see the motor segment
play through again let me just put put
this in context if you look at the
current year I I think the key key that
we kind of keep watching for is can we
continue to outperform the market if you
look at on a full year basis the
industry grew on motor roughly at about
8% IC lumbar's growth was roughly at
about 11 and a half% so we were able to
accrete market share
uh your point is right in in some sense
there has been a bit of a slight
slowdown in so far as new vehicle sales
is concerned but obviously I think when
you look at in terms of some of the
actions that the government and the
regulators have taken to kind of spur
demand on ground seems to be quite
promising and therefore to that extent
we do expect new vehicle sales to come
back at least when we look at FI26 but
more importantly for ISIS one of the
areas that we have actively focused on
is to see how we can significantly
improve our existing uh renewals of the
book that we have already under. So
hence you know quite promising uh and
lot more optimistic you know on uh motor
third party you're saying industry has
made representations and you haven't
heard anything as of now. what is the
kind of price hike that industry is
seeking in motor third party and also if
you could give us some sense of the loss
ratios there because if that third party
price hike doesn't come through it's
going to weigh on profitability isn't it
yeah so so let me just again put this in
context when I said that uh we expected
at the beginning of the year some lance
to semblance to come in the market uh it
was also in the context of motor as a
line of business and as I said we have
the numbers for the nine months so if
you look at the industry combined ratios
on motor this of course includes both
own damage and party there the combined
ratios have actually moved more adverse.
It has moved from 118 to 123. So hence
therefore is where we are all kind of
coming from to say that it's been 3 4
years of let's say no price change in
the context of third party. Uh any kind
of a price increase coming through I
think we will be very very positive at
what that number could be. I think we'll
leave it for the regulators and the
government to kind of decide in terms of
what they eventually give out. But the
good news the other other aspect that we
would be kind of very very closely
watching for Suri is next year which is
FI26 happens to be the year when the IDI
defined threshold on expense of
management wherein companies are
supposed to kind of meet the threshold
of uh expense of management to be within
30%. ISIS ro has always been within 30
companies have been exceeding that
threshold. So once if you see some
discipline coming through with respect
to the expenses of management that will
be a lot more positive as well in terms
of how uh demand could kind of spur in
so far as the market is concerned. You
know since you brought up that point
Gopal I must point out that our
colleague Yash who obviously covers the
insurance space you'd know him well he
put out a story a couple of weeks back
on this business of expenses of
management that maybe the regulator
could consider individual specific caps
on commissions in order to quote unquote
kind of discipline the industry because
the regulator seems to be feeling that
lower commissions are not being passed
on in the form of lower premiums uh to
the customer. uh just your thoughts on
this uh if you've heard anything and
what will this mean if there is a
specific individual cap on commission
not the the total expense. Yeah. So I
think so again Sub again just put this
in context. I think the the regulator
has been very very at it to make sure
that as an industry companies kind of
tow the line in so far as the expensive
management threshold is concerned which
is why they gave that three-year glide
path for players to kind of work
towards. As I said FI26 is the year when
you would see those companies having the
need to kind of come down within those.
So that would be a key regulatory watch
in terms of how companies exhibit that
trajectory. Gopal Gopal would the point
is overall cap is fine but there are
commissions and there are operating
expenses problem is IRDA feels that
commissions are through the roof and
that is so will that is that a problem
if it happens yeah so which is which is
what I was kind of responding to as in
to say that I think one of the things
that the regulator will be closely
watching for is this uh threshold in
terms of how companies are navigating so
long as they are able to see the
direction of change in terms of
companies going down in their overall
cost of distribution of which a very
large proportion of which will also be
the acquisition cost that they kind of
exhibit to distributors and that will be
a key uh key positive. Uh so hence
companies will have to actively work to
make sure that they bring down their
overall cost of distribution in that's
specifically in the context of
commissions at least in the context of
IC number which is what I was talking
about. I think we are very very clear
that uh in so far as the uh overall
expense of management is concerned we
will be well within the norms and two
have you and individual commissions cost
of acquisition of new business where are
you at right now so again just again let
me just put that in context even when
the regulator kind of introduced this
guidelines on long-term policies which
came into effect from October one
clearly the intent from a regulatory
standpoint was to try and see if we can
get the cost of acquisition amotized
over the contract period from the from
an ICO standpoint clearly we have stuck
to it to make sure that at least in so
far as the cost of acquisition for
long-term products are concerned it gets
kind of reminerated over the contract
period so that's how we are focused on
and making sure that we kind of well
operate within the laid down guidelines
the regulator has put in force have you
heard you know we the story was put out
a month about a month ago have you heard
any have you heard from the regulator
has there been any interaction on
commissions in the last one month for
the industry not just you yeah yeah as I
said the regulator is very closely
watching this particular space and I'm
sure we will wait for any further
actions on that. Okay. All right. Uh
we'll leave it there then. Gopal, thank
you very much. Appreciate you joining us
and running us through uh you know the
uh the the results and of course that 18
to 20% ROE guidance which I think is a
bit of a bump up as compared to what
they put out earlier. Uh and uh I mean
overall directionally things are looking
positive. Stocks recovered quite a bit
from the day low. I think started about
three and a half lower is down 0.8 on on
the commissions if I got him right
reading between the lines I think the
status quo is
that's what the regulator is doing in
this consultation and wait that's what
Yasha's story essentially was that you
know they're uh uh it was a warning to
health and general insurance against
rising commission payouts all